从此刻起,我们就和我们生命终结的那一刻,联系在了一起
From the moment we're conceived to the day we take our last breath,
科学,随着使用,触及到了我们每一个人
science,and the way we use it,touches every one of us.
科学被赋予了巨大的能力来拯救或孕育生命
Science has given immense power to save and nurture life.
但是变化的步伐如此之大,以至于我们很少花点时间
But the pace of change is so great that we don't often take time
停下来,看看我们已经走了多远
to stop and appreciate how far we've come.
这就是,我想和你分享这个时代最重要的十项科学进步的原因
That's why I want to share with you ten of the most important scientific advances of our time,
并且揭示一些摆在我们面前的事情
and reveal some of the things that might just lie ahead.
在这个节目的最后,我会要求你投票
At the end of the programme I'll be asking you to vote
选出最能改变你的世界的进步
for the advance you think has done the most to change your world.
这对我们的社会有着巨大的冲击
It's had a massive impact on our society.
它确实改变了你的生活,不是吗？
It's really changed your life,hasn't it？
所以,你是完美的仿生女人？
So you're the perfect bionic woman？ Yeah!
还是赢家？嗯,这取决于你.
And the winner？ Well,it's up to you.
科学如何改变我们的世界
这是个人的一小步,却是人类的一大步.
It's one small step for man,one giant leap for mankind.
过去50年中已经看到科学改造我们的世界.
The last 50 years has seen science transform our world.
半个世纪以来,它战胜了无数的疾病
In half a century,it's tackled countless diseases,
把人送上月球
put men on the moon,
彻底改变我们的沟通方式.
and completely changed the way we communicate.
这是我的科学十大进步.
These are my top ten advances.
有些可能是你期望的,有些可能会让你惊讶.
Some things you may expect,others you may find more surprising.
第一项科学进步,差点就没被包括在我的十大进步中,
The first advance to take place in my top ten almost didn't make it,
因为它太古老了！
because it's very nearly too old!
这是一个一些女性喜欢,但又假装不感兴趣的
There are some women who prefer at least to pretend they're not interested in it.
喜欢被男性亲近
And who like to be approached by the man.
但是,对于一切的伟大时代
But for all its great age,
它让很多人非常高兴
it's made a lot of people extremely happy.
啊,我怎么就失去了贞操！
Ah,how I lost my virginity!
老天爷,我母亲就有一个合适的
Cor blimey. My mother would have had a fit.
我们有一场比赛,我和这个女孩,看谁能把它首先移开,这很可怕！
We had a race,me and this girl,to see who could have it off first. It was terrible!
但是我们都玩得很高兴
But we were having a wonderful time!
当我还是一个医科学生时,
When I was a medical student,which is longer ago than I actually care to mention,
发生了一场技术革命
there was a revolution
有些人认为这改变了我们的社会.那就是避孕药.
which some people claim transformed our society. It was,of course,the contraceptive pill.
1961年,这小小的药片诞生于英国
In 1961,the Pill was released in Britain.
这个日期印在了药片的每一面
The day is printed by the side of every pill.
并让她能记起这是哪一天,
And providing she can remember what day it is,
女性可以非常确定今天她吃药没有
a woman can be quite sure whether or not she has taken today's pill.
制造商尽最大努力使它们万无一失
The manufacturers do their best to make them foolproof -
他们不想失去他们的声誉,或者称之为"飞行员的错误"
they don't want to lose their reputation over what might be called "pilot's error".
今天,我们把它视为理所当然,但在当时,这是革命性的.
Today we take it for granted,but for that first generation,it was revolutionary.
我是个学生的老师
I was a student teacher
在当时,并且,嗯
during that time,and,er,
学校周围到处都是
it got round in college
有一个医生在Doncaster发放避孕药,
that there was a certain doctor in Doncaster that would give the Pill,
所以我们都抄捷径跑去.
so we all made a beeline for that.
有趣的是,所有的病人,我们都称之为“太太“
Interestingly enough,all the patients,we were all called "Mrs"
当你被喊进去看医生.
when you were called in to see the doctor.
在那儿,你就不是“小姐”了
You weren't "Miss" even there.
我们去一个私人诊所,还要遮掩一下,所以我带上一个纸袋.
We knew there was one private clinic,except you had to pay for it,so I had to take a paper round.
避孕药在社会大变革的时候爆发式的出现,
The Pill exploded onto the scene at a time of great social upheaval,
而它自己也成了这一巨大变化的一部分.
and itself became a huge part of that change.
我感觉被解放了.从怀孕的恐惧中解放出来,太不可思议了.
I felt quite liberated. Just to be free of that fear of becoming pregnant was amazing.
我意识到我已经控制了自己的生活
I was aware that I was taking control of my own life.
当时报纸上有很多关于避孕药的报道"哦,它会让女性行为不检点"
There were lots of things in the newspapers about the Pill,"Oh,it'll make women tarty,"
所有这些事,你知道.对我来说并不是那样.
and everything,you know. It wasn't like that for me.
我可以有计划的安排,对我来说非常重要的孩子和事业.
I could plan my children and my career,which was so important to me.
但是没有人预见到的是,使用避孕药把生育推迟
But what nobody foresaw was that the Pill meant that more women
的妇女会有更多不孕不育的风险.
have tended to leave child-bearing later and risk infertility.
但是它能让更多的人自由的规划、平衡、改变,让生活变得更好.
But that freedom to plan has,on balance,changed most people's lives for the better.
因为这个原因,避孕药位列我的十大科技进步之一.
And for that reason,the Pill has to be in my top ten.
它很小,但它的对我们的社会产生了巨大的冲击.
It's tiny but it's had a massive impact on our society.
它产生的影响是过去50年最重要的进步之一.
Its liberating influence has been one of the most important advances in the last 50 years.
正如避孕药在二十世纪六十年代,改变了妇女的生活,
Just as the Pill transformed women's lives in the 1960s,
科学有一次改变了我们和避孕的关系.
science is changing our relationship with contraception again.
Bill和Rachel要开始试验一种新的避孕方式
Bill and Rachel are just about to start a trial
不需要像以前那样每天采取措施.
for a new contraceptive that doesn't need to be taken every day.
你已经有了三个孩子,你有怀孕时,每次服用避孕药？
You've had three children,and you got pregnant when on the Pill each time？
是的.与避孕药无关,只与我们的做法有关.
Yeah. Nothing to do with the Pill,just to do with us.
你没有正确使用？这是一个.
You didn't take it properly？ That's the one.
你试过什么避孕方法？
So what methods of contraception have you tried？
我们已经试过节欲,因为他在海军,所以他常常外出工作一段时间.
We've tried abstinence,cos he was in the Navy,so that worked for a while,with him going away.
我们试过在开始的时候用避孕套.
We tried condoms briefly in the beginning.
为什么你不想再吃避孕药了？
And why didn't you want to take the Pill any more？
我真的很不接受它
I'm really not good at taking it
我很放心不应该有不同化学物质,肯定知道我会忘记压力.
and I'd be relieved to not have different chemicals,and the stress of knowing I'd forgotten.
And you didn't mind your husband having the chemicals？ No. Bash on.
I think it would be great for him to take some responsibility.
The contraceptive they're about to try is actually for Bill,not Rachel.
Now,I know what you might be thinking -
and if I were a woman,I might not trust a man,
even a reliable fireman like Bill to take the Pill,either.
But this pill
is actually a course of injections which will leave Bill temporarily infertile.
So what on earth made you take part in this trial？
Mmm... For me,it's just about being able to take over
the role of contraception from Rachel,and me being responsible for that,
rather than it all being left to Rache.
And did the side-effects that they talk about
on the male contraception worry you？
There are a few side effects that they did warn us about,like weight gain,
acne,irritability.
Did they tell you you might develop breasts？
They did say that. Yes.
You're a fireman,aren't you？ I am.
Did you discuss it with your mates at work？
Strangely,no.
Why？ I mean... the ribbing I'll get,never mind...
It's a really macho environment.
Yeah. It is I suppose,it's fertility and a guy,like,you know,I'm really butch...
And do you understand the science of how it actually works？ I don't.
Would you like to know？ Yes,please.
Let me explain it to you.
It's actually quite surprising,and in some ways
it's not dissimilar from the female pill,the oral contraception that women take.
And essentially,it really works in the brain,so if this is a body,
the brain sends out a signal
to make an egg or make a sperm,OK？
Now,the pill is a hormone which inhibits the brain by telling it the egg is already being made
when it's not being made,so the brain thinks the woman is ovulating so it stops sending the message,
and that's exactly what happens with the male contraception,too,so if you're given the male hormone,
that tells the brain,"I'm making lots of sperm,"
so it just shuts down. So it's quite an elegant idea,
and that feedback is
one of the most interesting examples in biology of how the body works.
The idea is that the injections will deal with Bill's biological feedback for months at a time.
这是他的主意.
This was his idea.
因此我的10大科技中的第一项——避孕药,诞生于大变革的六十年代,
So the first entry on my list is the Pill - revolutionary in the '60s,
在在之后的50年里仍然不断地改进自身.
and still reinventing itself almost 50 years later.
太奇妙了
Fantastic.
我的下一个科学进步也显著的影响了我们的生活-
My next advance has also had a dramatic impact on our lives -
事实上,它是如此的重要,以至于在我的十大科学进步名单中,扮演了重要的角色
in fact,it's so significant that it's played a part in almost all of the other inventions on my list.
当我还在念书时,我在一个无线电厂里工作
When I was a schoolboy,I worked in a radio factory.
Benzimra先生一周付我5英镑
I was being paid five pounds a week by Mr Benzimra,
把密密麻麻的零部件焊上这样的印刷电路板
a princely sum,to solder little components onto a printed circuit board like this.
很快,我意识到这就像横渡大西洋般困难,而一个人改变了整个进程
Little did I realise that across the Atlantic,a man was going to revolutionise the whole process.
一个名叫Jack Kilby的工程师发明了一种缩小这些部件的方法.
An engineer called Jack Kilby found a way to shrink all these components
把这些部件都集中在一个很小的东西里
into one extraordinary,and tiny thing.
就是这个,不起眼的微型芯片
It's this,the humble microchip.
自从50年前发明了这个,
And since its invention 50 years ago,there's been more medical
我们在医学和科技方面取得的进步,比人类历史上任他何其时期都多
and scientific progress than in any other period in human history.
微型芯片是我的科学十大进步之一.从我们早上醒来
The microchip has to be in our top ten. From the moment we wake up
到我们晚上睡觉,它影响了我们生活中的方方面面
to the moment we go to bed,it affects every part of our lives.
没有微芯片,我们就没有笔记本电脑.
Without the microchip,there would be no laptop,
没有银行卡,没有手机.
no cash card,no mobile phone.
简单的说,没有微型芯片,我们将仍然生活在20世纪70年代
In short,without the microchip,we'd still be living in the 1970s.
让我惊讶的是,当年我焊接的老式电路板的所有这些部件
It amazes me that today all those elements of the old electronic circuit board
现在只能在显微镜下看见
I soldered together as a schoolboy can only be seen down a microscope.
我们只是把它们做的更小了
And now the technology is set to make it even smaller.
我在伦敦纳米技术中心
I'm in the London Centre for Nanotechnology,
这里用最小的粒子来制造东西
where they make the smallest particles that are possible to be made.
因为这个原因,我得穿上防尘服,因为哪怕是空气中的
And the reason why I'm wearing the garb is because any skin cell
皮肤细胞都会污染他们的东西.
in the atmosphere would contaminate what they do.
在我的指尖上
And here on my fingertip
是一个小小的电路板
is a little electronic chip.
在这个电路板上他们能放下5千万个晶体管
On this chip,they can fit 50 million transistors.
这个,下一代微电路版
This,the next generation of mini-miracles,
目前它是最小的.
is as small as it gets...for now.
这个晶圆上的每一个电子元件都比病毒还小
Each electronic component in these circuits is smaller than a virus.
这意味着微型设备将会像病毒一样,
And that miniaturisation means that chips,like viruses,
以我们无法想象的方式进入我们的生活
are getting closer to us than we could have possibly imagined.
现在这儿就有一样东西.这个微型芯片完全由可食用的物质制成.
Now,here's a thing. This microchip is made of a substance which is entirely edible.
因此一旦你吞下它,它就会被胃酸分解
So when you swallow it,it gets dissolved by the acid
然后发送一个信号到你胳膊上的接收器上
in your stomach,and it sends a signal to a plaster on your arm.
这就是胳膊上的接收器 - ow! -
And the plaster on your arm - ow! -
这个小小的设备就像一个接收机,如果你没有按时吃下你的药片
has got this little device like a radio,and if you haven't taken your pill...
我的手机会得到这个消息,并且说"你今天没有按时吃药"
I get a message on my phone saying,"You haven't your pill today."
但是任何技术都是一柄双刃剑
But there's a darker side to all technology.
微型芯片的广泛应用确实带来一些问题
The sheer proliferation of the microchip does bring some concerns.
我站在皮卡迪里广场,你可要知道在50码范围内
It's worth considering that within 50 yards of where I'm standing in Piccadilly Circus,
至少有50部监视摄像机记录下我的每一个动作
there must be at least 50 surveillance cameras recording every movement we make,
这些海量的数据我们并没有管理好.
amassing a huge amount of data over which we have no control.
我们如何处理这些问题,是一个日益严峻的挑战.
How we deal with these issues is an increasing challenge.
存储的个人数据在很大程度上是不受管制,
Storage of personal data is largely unregulated,and fraud,
在虚拟世界中诈骗、盗窃和丢失个人数据,让越来越多的人开始担忧
theft and loss of privacy in the virtual world worries many people.
尽管如此,微芯片仍然在我的科学进步名单中
But in spite of all this,the chip is on my list,
我们不能否认,没有它很多其他领域的进展将会变得不可能
and we shouldn't forget that without it,many of the other advances wouldn't have been possible.
包括下面这一个
Including this next one.
第三项科学进步是我故事中的一个设备
At number three on my list is a device in whose story I,
或者说是我的兔子Wilhelmina,在这儿扮演一个主角
or rather my rabbit Wilhelmina,played here by an actor,had a starring role.
好吧,一个角色,反正
Well,a role,anyway.
我在酒吧里和一些物理学的朋友喝了一晚上的啤酒,
I met some physics friends in the bar having a beer one evening,
他们说“我们刚刚建造了这台有着不计其数电线的机器”
and they said,"We've just built this machine with lots of wire
还有天花板蜡和老式电视屏幕
"and string and ceiling wax and an old television screen
它叫做磁共振图像机
"and it's called a Magnetic Resonance Image machine,
"你想把你的兔子放进去吗？"
"and would you like to put your rabbit in it？"
所以我们就下到了Hammersmith医院的地下室
So we went down to the sub-basement of Hammersmith Hospital
我们很温柔的把Wilhelmina放了进去
and we put Wilhelmina gently into the machine.
我有一点点但心它,经过20分钟的烹饪
I was a bit worried about it,and then after 20 minutes of cooking,
我们得到了一张照片,看起来有点像这个.
we got a photograph,and it looked a bit like this.
只是一片模糊
Just a blur.
我并没有意识到这将是这个时代的一场革命
And I didn't have the sense to realise that this was going to be quite revolutionary in its time.
我想我的兔子是第一个拍这种照片的活体生物之一.
I think my pet rabbit was one of the first living organisms to be photographed like this.
这项技术,这在当时刚刚起步,后来成为核磁共振扫描仪.
And the technology,which was then in its infancy,went on to become the MRI scanner.
在我的大部分医学生涯,X射线是检查人体最有效的手段
For much of my career in medicine,X-rays were the most effective way of looking inside the human body.
但是它并没有给出除骨头以外其他器官的清晰图像
But they didn't give a particularly clear image of all the organs beyond our bones.
核磁共振扫描改变了一切.
MRI scanning changed all that.
工程师最初用核磁共振来检查金属内部.
Engineers first used MRI to look inside metals.
现在我们可以直接看到生物组织.
Now we're able see directly into living tissues
这给了我们不可思议的新视野,来观察最复杂的人体组织结构.
and that's given amazing new insights into the most complicated organ in the human body.
我觉得很谦逊,而这个空间,这个没有生命的物体,
I find it really rather humbling that this space,this inanimate object,
这个大脑曾经是某个人感受到愤怒、悲伤、爱的地方.
this brain was once the place where somebody felt angry,felt sad,and loved.
另人惊讶的是,直到最近,我们都不知道它是如何真正工作.
And the extraordinary thing is that until quite recently,we had no idea how it was really working.
令人振奋的研究来自剑桥大学,利用MRI（核磁共振成像扫描仪）,研究大脑如何思考.
Exciting research at the University of Cambridge is using the MRI scanner to see how the mind works.
罗伯特,你好.很高兴见到你.
Robert,hello. Nice to see you.
在隔壁扫描室的是一个志愿者,我从来没见过他.
In the scanner next door is a willing volunteer I've never met.
我要你朝这边.而不是看窗户？
I want you to face this way. And not to look in the window？
这样我就看不到你的课题.
So I can't see your subject.
问一些简单的是或否的问题,
By asking some simple yes or no questions,
我要试着找出一些关于他的,或者是她.
I'm going to try to find out a bit about him. Or her.
如果在扫描仪里的人想要表达“是”
If the person in the scanner is trying to convey a yes,
你就会看到运动前皮层周围呈现亮红色
you'll see a bright red area of activity around his pre-motor cortex,
顶部的右边,头部的中间.
right at the top,in the middle of the head.
如果在扫描仪里的人想要说“否”
If the person in the scanner is trying to convey a no,
你会看到同样的区域呈现高亮,
you'll see the same area of the brain lighting up
只不过变成了蓝绿色.
but it will be a blue-green colour.
你是男性吗？
Are you a man？
该你了.
There you go.
我很确信此时这个人在表达“是”
I'm pretty confident this person is conveying a yes at this stage.
你超过六英尺高？
Are you over six foot high？
现在是绿色,他在说“否”
He's now got a green area,so this is signalling a no answer,
这就意味着这个人实际上没有六英尺高.
which would mean that actually this man is shorter than six foot.
我们并不能实际看到大脑说“是”或“否”
We can't actually see the brain think yes or no.
这对于一台MRI（核磁共振成像仪）来说并不是一件太难的事.
That would be too difficult even for an MRI machine.
我们要求志愿者想像打网球
What our volunteer was asked to do was to imagine playing tennis
当他回答“是”并照做时,大脑的相关区域
when he wants to say yes,and when he does,the area of the brain
运动和想象,他的运动前皮层
which deals with movement,his motor cortex,
显示出活跃增加,用MRI很容易看到.
shows increased activity,and that is easy for the MRI to see.
这是我们最后一个问题.
And this is our last question.
你有胡子吗？
Do you have facial hair？
相关区域再次活跃起来.
Again,pretty obvious activation.
我会说这家伙的要么留着胡须要么有胡子.
I would say that this guy's either got a beard or a moustache.
Hi!
非常感谢你,我是罗伯特.温斯顿
Thank you so much. I'm Robert Winston.
你肯定没有六英尺高.
You're certainly not six-foot high,we got that right.
最近的一项研究使用这种技术,使我们可以观测并与一些
One recent study using this technique has given us an insight into communication
被认为是永久植物人的病人进行的沟通.
with some patients in what was thought to be a permanent vegetative state.
最近我们看到了一个病人,他在这种状态下已经五年了,
We've seen a patient recently,who'd actually been in that situation for five years
他能够以这种技术来传达是”或“不是”的反应.
and he was able to use this technique to convey yes and no responses.
这当然不是所有病人的情况,但我们现在知道,
It's certainly not the case for all patients,but we now know there are a sub-group of these patients
这些患者中的一些有可能比我们想象能做的更多.
who probably can do more than we think they can.
这很可怕,不是？
It's quite scary,isn't it？
难道你不觉得真的很惊人,
Do you not find that really quite amazing,
而且符合我们的人性？
but also very on the edge of our humanity？
它是,它是许多人发现很难去思考,
It is and it is something that many people find quite difficult to think about,
你的思想会被困在你的身体,而无法交流.
the idea that you could be trapped inside your body and unable to communicate.
幸运的是我们找到了一种方法,让一些病人能够绕过这种困境.
Hopefully we've found a way where some of these patients can get around that issue.
这其实是测量你体内血液流量的变化.
Essentially what you're measuring is changes in blood flow.
我们观测大脑中的活跃区域.
We're looking at the areas of the brain that are working hardest.
这些活跃区域需要更多的血液来提供氧气,这也正是我们测量的.
They're drawing blood,which is delivering oxygen and that's what we're measuring.
我不可能看到有人用这台机器说,"他认为我是个白痴. "
I couldn't look at somebody with this machine and say,"He thinks I am a complete moron."
不,也许那是真的,但是至少你不会知道.
No,that might be true,but at least you won't know that.
无论如何MRI是我们研究大脑如何思考的重要途径.
Undoubtedly,the MRI machine has been the most important way of seeing how our brain works.
它本身就有资格作为过去50年最重要的科学进步之一.
And that alone qualifies it as one of the most significant advances in the last 50 years.
对于我来说,它脱颖而出的是将它非凡的能力
But what really makes it stand out for me is its extraordinary ability
用于医学上来改善生命.
to transform lives through its use in medicine.
17岁的Elyse Westrip在她11岁时,就患有严重的癫痫症.
17-year-old Elyse Westrip has had severe epilepsy since she was 11.
近来,核磁共振扫描发现,癫痫是由于大脑肿瘤造成的.
MRI scans have recently revealed that the seizures are due to a brain tumour.
明亮的区域就是异常的区域.
This bright area here is the area that is abnormal.
我们现在要做的就是确定如何关闭该区域
What we need to do now is determine how close
同时又避免影响其重要功能.
that area to be removed is to parts that carry out vital functions.
虽然肿瘤可以摘除,
Though it's been decided that the tumour can be removed,
但坏消息是这个肿瘤非常靠近她的视神经.
the bad news is that it's dangerously close to her optic nerve.
手术有可能导致部分失明.
The operation carries the risk of partial blindness.
但是对于Elyse来说,这个险值得冒.
But for Elyse,it's a risk worth taking.
我试着忘记风险,
I'm trying to forget the risks
只想积极的,
and just think positive,
手术后好起来的事情.
the good things about having the surgery.
我感到我正越来越好,
I feel I'm going to get better.
我可以改变我现在的生活,恢复到以前那样.
I can change my life back to how it was before.
癫痫变得很糟糕,我决定提前离开学校,因为我应付不了了.
The epilepsy got so bad I decided to leave school early because I couldn't cope any more.
因为我的病我非常烦恼.
I just got upset a lot that I was different.
它在很大程度上改变了我的生活.
It did change my life a lot.
肿瘤位于Elyse大脑内部5厘米处.
The tumour is buried five centimetres into Elyse's brain.
在过去,这种手术
In the past,patients undergoing this operation
会让病人承担很大的脑损伤风险.
would have run a significant risk of suffering brain damage.
但是感谢MRI技术的使用,Elyse将面对的风险大大降低了.
But thanks to MRI,the risk to Elyse is greatly reduced.
在 MRI 新的应用中,扫描得到的图像映射到外科医生的显微镜中,
In a new use of MRI,the scans are mapped onto an image seen in the surgeon's microscope,
这可以引导医生避开正常的脑组织切除肿瘤.
and that will help him navigate past the healthy brain to remove the tumour,
肿瘤显示为虚线.
which is shown as a dotted line.
经过了近五个小时的手术,肿瘤被成功摘除.
After nearly five hours of surgery,the tumour is finally removed.
这就是取出来的.
This is the specimen that's come out so far.
它在颞极前四厘米处,这是脑肿瘤的确切位置.
It's the front four centimetres of the temporal pole,which is exactly where the brain tumour is.
我认为肿瘤就在这个位置,最底部的右侧.
I think the brain tumour is in this bit here,right at the very bottom.
Elyse再次接受了扫描,确认已经没有脑肿瘤.
And then Elyse is scanned again to ensure that none of the tumour remains.
这张照片看起来不可思议.太神奇了.
The pictures look amazing. Fantastic.
两个月后当Elyse过她18岁生日时我去拜访她.
Two months later and I'm off to visit Elyse on her 18th birthday.
你好,生日快乐！这是送给你的花.
Hello. Happy birthday. There's some flowers for you.
我很高兴地看到,她完全康复了.
I'm delighted to see that she's made a full recovery.
令人惊讶的是,就在手术前几个星期,她曾一天里发作多达8次.
It's amazing that only a few weeks ago before the operation,she was having up to eight seizures a day.
你现在还有任何发作吗？
Are you having any seizures at all？
- 没有.- 那这确实改变了你的生活？
None. So it's really changed your life？
是的.
Yeah.
这太不可思议了！
That's fantastic.
外科医生的技能和MRI技术的奇妙结合
It's miraculous to see how the surgeons' skill and MRI technology
已经完全改变了Elyse的生活.
has totally transformed Elyse's life.
在过去50年创新、发明和发现以前所未有的规模出现.
The past 50 years has seen innovation,invention and discovery on an unprecedented scale.
我选择我认为是最好的,过去半个世纪里的十大科学进展.
I'm choosing what I think are the very best,the top ten scientific advances of the past half century.
到目前为止,我们已经看到了避孕药对妇女
So far we've seen how the pill has revolutionised women's
甚至每个人的生活产生的重大影响.
and indeed everybody's lives.
我们已经或多或少看了微芯片在应用上的神奇作用
We've looked at the almost miraculous effect of the microchip on,well,more or less everything,
透过 MRI 扫描,我们可以一窥令人惊奇的大脑的神奇能力
and we've marvelled at our godlike ability to peer into the mind,thanks to MRI scanning.
接下来还有七个科学进步.
There are still seven of my top ten to come
在节目的最后,你有机会选出你最喜欢的科学进步.
and after the programme,you'll get a chance to vote on which is your favourite,
最棒中的最棒
the best of the best.
与此同时,在这个名单中
Meanwhile,on with the list.
我的第四个选择,虽然相当熟悉,但有可能拯救地球.
My fourth choice,which though rather familiar,has the potential to save the planet.
我当然不会把它排除在外.
I certainly wouldn't be without this.
这是我最喜欢的发明之一.电筒
It's one of my favourite inventions. It's the electric torch.
但光的应用发展的重大进步
But the great advance in the use of light came 50 years ago
是在50年前发明了激光,把光线集中在一个非常小的区域内,非常精确.
with the invention of the laser,which concentrates the light down a very narrow beam,very precisely.
这是自从人类点亮第一支蜡烛以来,光学的最重大进步.
It's the greatest advance in the technology of light since mankind lit its first candle.
一束激光产生的光线如此集中,以至于它可以用来点火、切割和摧毁.
A laser produces light that's so concentrated it can burn,cut and destroy.
从一开始,这个破坏力
From the very beginning,this destructive power
引发了人科幻作家的想象力.
has sparked the imagination of science fiction writers.
他选择了自己的死亡！
He has chosen his own death!
但是这种力量也可以用来做有益的事,这就是为什么它在我的十大科学进步名单中.
But the force can also be used for good and that's why it's in my top ten.
这是功率为1瓦的激光.
Here's a laser of a power of one watt.
如果你不想自己划亮火柴,你可以把它放在这束光里.
If you don't want to use your energy to strike your match,you can just hold it in the beam of light.
一束1瓦的激光可以点燃火柴.
A one-watt laser can light a match.
想象一下
Imagine,then,the power
500万亿瓦激光.
of a 500 trillion watt laser.
这正是他们建在加利福尼亚州国家点火中心的装置
That's exactly what they've built here at the National Ignition Facility in California,
在那儿,工程师们刚刚建完世界上最强大的激光.
where engineers have just finishing constructing the laser to end all lasers.
事实上,192束世界上功率最大的激光
In fact,192 of the world's most powerful lasers,
聚焦在氢原子上.
all focused on a tiny hydrogen target.
如果它们能在同一时间照射目标
If they can be made to strike at the same time,
我所说的同一时间是十亿分之一秒,
and when I say the same time,I mean within one billionth of a second,
这时原子中的能量就会被释放出来
then the energy inside the atoms will be released,
释放出超过整个美国国家电网
creating in one moment 500 times more energy
500倍的能量.
than the entire American National Grid.
这不可思议的能量来自核聚变
This incredible energy release is from nuclear fusion.
什么是核聚变能量？核聚变能量就是太阳内部的能量来源.
What is fusion power？ Fusion power is what's going on inside the sun.
当我们把氢原子聚合到一起,就会发生核聚变,
When we crush hydrogen together,we get this fusion to happen,
我们把物质转化成能量
we turn mass into energy
能量释放出来,如果我们收集这些能量.
and that energy comes out and if we can collect it,
把它转换为电能,驱动我们文明的能源.这就是核聚变能量.
and turn it into electricity,that's what we want to power our civilization. That's fusion power.
这就是我们希望在这个靶室发生的.
That's what we hope to make happen in this target chamber.
这种能源让人激动的是没有污染问题
What is so exciting about this energy,we have no issue of pollution
不会造成全球变暖.
and we have no issue of global climate warming.
那是我们的梦想.充满梦想和希望的核聚变发电,
That is the dream. That has always been the dream of fusion energy
- 在这里我们将会实现它.- 没有核废物？
and hopefully,we'll be able to do it here. And no nuclear waste？
对,没有核废物.
No nuclear waste. Right.
我知道这套装置的未来几年内
I just know that in this facility in the next couple of years,
有望找到解决之道.
hopefully one,we will find out that we can do it.
事实上,在这个实验室里Ed和他的同事
Effectively,within this chamber,Ed and his colleagues
尝试创造并捕获这种恒星的能量
are trying to create and capture the power of a star
将原子聚合成质子.
by fusing protons in an atom.
如此强大的能量来源,如果它可以被开发利用,
A source of energy so powerful that if it could be harnessed,
将提供更便宜,更清洁的可再生能源
it would provide the Holy Grail of cheaper,cleaner renewable energy
并减少对化石燃料的依赖.
and reduce our dependence on fossil fuels.
不同寻常的是这台庞大的装置
What's utterly extraordinary is that all this energy
产生的所有能量都来自那里.
that you're generating from this vast machine is actually in that.
让我看看那个小小的胶囊.
Just show me that little capsule.
这胶囊就是存储氢燃料的地方.
That capsule is where the hydrogen fuel resides.
氢在这里处于接近绝对零度的状态,激光照射进来并加热它.
It resides there at near absolute zero and the laser light comes in and it heats up this can.
当外壳炸开时氢原子被加速到每小时150万公里
When the shell explodes,that hydrogen implodes at nearly 1.5 million kilometres per hour
这就是我们制造核聚变的方法.
and that's how we get that fusion to happen.
这种使用激光的想法不仅解决物理学的一大难题
The idea of using the laser to solve one of the great problems of physics,
还可以生产清洁能源,有可能会拯救我们的星球.
the production of green energy,which might save the planet
利用核聚变.这似乎是一个发展激光器的非常重要的原因.
using nuclear fusion. That seems to be a really important reason for developing lasers.
有趣的是当发明激光时
It's interesting to remember that when lasers were invented,
没人能想象到激光会有这么多用途.
no-one imagined how many uses we'd have for them.
很不幸,但事实是战争会促使我们在某些方面取得重大进展.
It's unfortunate but true that war is when we make some of our greatest advances.
我的下一条就复杂得多.
And my next owes much to conflict.
我是晚上在阿富汗南部巡逻时踩到一个简易爆炸装置.
I was in southern Afghanistan on patrol at night and stepped on an IED.
我还记得看到了一片闪光,然后感觉被抛到了半空中又摔下来,
I remember seeing the flash,the feeling of going through the air,landing,
距我15英尺的同伴被炸死.
and I got blown about 15 feet away from the lads.
我立刻明白发生了什么,马上检查自己
I knew what happened straightaway cos I checked myself
看看我的手指、我的手还在不在.
to see if I had all my fingers,my hands.
我一摸我的腿,“它不在了,够公平的”我想.
I got to my leg,and I thought,"That ain't there. Fair enough."
我检查另一条腿,它严重出血.
I checked the other leg and that was bleeding badly.
骨头和其他的东西全碎了,我想等我再醒来时这条腿就没了.
All shattered bones and everything else,so I knew that probably wouldn't be there when I woke up.
该你了.
There you go.
直到前不久,Sam 都在也不能站起来走路,
Until recently,Sam would have never walked again,
但是现在生物力学科学在模仿我们身体的
but now the science of biomechanics is getting closer than ever before
复杂性和精密度上都比以前有了更大进展.
to mimicking the complexity and sophistication of our own bodies.
在 Headley Court 军队康复中心,
At Headley Court Military Rehabilitation Centre,
医生正在帮助数百名像Sam这样受伤的士兵.
doctors are helping hundreds of injured soldiers like Sam.
Sam,你什么时候受的伤？
Sam,when were you injured？
八月初.
Beginning of August.
现在你已经能够行走了？
So you're already walking.
这就是？5个月？
So that's what？ Five months？
- 对,是的.- 这是相当了不起. - 是啊.
About that,yeah. Which is rather impressive. Yeah.
这是你的一个巨大努力？ 想必这一定是.
Has that been a massive effort for you？ Presumably,it must have been.
确实充满挑战.一直想超过和我类似情况的朋友.
More of a challenge,really. Been trying to beat some Para friends of mine.
你在不断的挑战你自己？
Do you compete amongst yourselves？
我们之间有很多竞争,看谁最先离开这儿.
There's a lot of competition between us to see who can be out quickest.
- 作为士兵你更有竞争力.- 肯定
Being soldiers,you tend to be competitive. Definitely.
令人惊奇的是Sam的假肢是由电脑控制的.
The amazing thing about Sam's artificial legs is that they're controlled by a computer.
电脑在哪儿？
Where is the computer in this？
在膝关节的后面.
It's just behind the knee joint.
在胫骨安装了一些传感器,
In the shin we've got some strain gauges
这些传感器每秒发送50次数据给电脑,来调节液压系统.
and they give 50 readings per second back to the computer,which then regulates the hydraulics.
这真的能让这个人工膝盖能如此稳定的正常行走.
That's really what makes this knee so stable in normal walking.
在这之前,失去双腿对Sam造成了怎样的影响？
In the early days,an injury would have resulted in what for Sam？
他一生的大部分时间可能都得坐在轮椅上.
He'd have probably been sat in a wheelchair for most of his life.
现在,他花费几乎所有的时间在他的双腿,走路.
Now he spends pretty much all his time on his legs,walking about.
- 所以这改变了他的生活？- 绝对是.
So it's life-changing？ Absolutely. Yeah.
现在没有任何事你不能做,就像你过去那样.
There isn't anything that you can't do now that you used to be able to do.
滑雪,游泳,跑步,骑自行车.
Skiing,swimming,running,going on the bike.
你期望回到滑雪场？当然可以.
You'd expect to get back on the ski slopes？ Absolutely.
如果你有正确的东西,正确的态度,
If you've got the right stuff,the right attitude,you can pretty much carry on with everything
你几乎可以像以前那样做任何事情.没有东西能阻止你.
as good as before. Nothing stopping you.
不仅受伤的士兵可以从新技术中获益.
And it is isn't only wounded soldiers that are benefiting from this new technology.
从头部到脚趾,生物力学是设法修理和更换大自然的精心调校的“机器”.
From head to toe,biomechanics is finding ways to repair and replace nature's finely-tuned machine.
生物力学的雄心是制造要真正的一体化假肢.
The ambition for biomechanics is for prosthetics to be truly integrated.
为达成这个目标,研究者需要收集使用者的想法.
And for that,they would need to be controlled by the user's mind.
但是直到前不久,介入大脑同步工作还是无法实现的.
But until recently,interfering with the workings of the brain just wasn't an option.
但是今天,这开始有了变化
But today,that's all starting to change.
深入研究和操作大脑的能力有许多潜在的好处,
The ability to delve into and manipulate the brain has
而不只是控制假肢.
many potential benefits,not only for the control of prosthetic limbs.
Diane Hire 患有抑郁症超过20年.
Diane Hire suffered from depression for more than 20 years.
她的病是如此严重,它甚至驱使她试图三次自杀.
Her illness was so crippling that it even drove her to attempt suicide three times.
告诉我很沮丧是什么感觉.
So tell me what it's like to be depressed.
它很可怕,就像身处一个黑暗的洞穴里.
It's awful,it's like being in a dark cave.
周围没有人,孤独、寒冷.
Nobody around,cold,lonely.
如果你有抑郁症,你绝对没有活下去的愿望.
If you have depression,you have absolutely no desire to live
就是这样,日复一日
and it just is like that day after day after day.
其实,我想我从中感觉到了死亡
Actually,I guess I felt dead inside,
我就像一个活着,却谈论死亡的人.
I was like a living,talking dead person.
我尝试过几种药,我也试过ECT治疗,电休克治疗.
I tried several medications and I also tried ECT,electroconvulsive therapy.
那些同样可怕
That was pretty awful too!
还有最后一种手段来尝试控制她的抑郁症,Diane接受了一项
In a last-ditch attempt to control her depression,Diane underwent
开创性的手术,希望由此控制自己的灾难性抑郁症.
groundbreaking surgery in the hope of controlling her devastating depression.
经过5小时的手术,电极植入了她大脑内8厘米深的地方.
In a five-hour operation,electrodes were directly inserted eight centimetres into her brain.
为了测试电极位置是否正确,Diane在手术中醒来
To check the electrodes were in the correct position,Diane was woken up
以便调整电脉冲.
during the procedure,so that the impulses could be adjusted.
你知道,当我醒来,他们说,
You know,when I woke up,they said,
"我们现在将打开它,你要告诉我们你的感觉."
"We're going to turn this on now and you let us know how things are feeling."
我头一次感到无法形容的温暖,然后他们调到另外一个设置,我的心开始飞舞.
And at first I felt pretty warm,and then they turned it to another setting,and my heart was galloping.
你感觉如何？笑一个.
How you feeling？ Starting to smile.
我感觉很快乐.然后我脸上出现了一个大大的笑容.
I feel happy. Then all of a sudden,I got this great big grin on my face.
之后,他们让我重新入睡
And after that,they put me back to sleep
以便结束手术.
to finish up the surgery.
你突然间就感觉到快乐？
So you immediately felt happy suddenly？
是的,立刻,对于我来说,那像什么？
Oh yes,for me it was instantaneous. What was that like？
不可思议
Amazing.
就像我的大脑在做体操.
It was almost like my brain was doing gymnastics.
这就像我以前去上班时的感觉,你知道.
You know it's how I used to feel when I would go to work
还有……
and...and...
在一个美好的周末,做一些好的事情.
you know,have good weekends and do things.
Diane和这个连接在她身体上,像心脏起搏器一样的系统共同生活了三年
Three years later and Diane lives with the system wired into her own body,much like a pacemaker.
它安装在哪儿？
And where do the wires run？
控制器在你的胸部,是吗？
The control box is in your chest,isn't it？
是的.从这儿开始然后,顺着我脑袋后面
Right. They start here,and then they go down the back of my skull,
再到我的脖子后面,绕一圈
down the back of my neck and around and plug into
然后插入我胸部的电池盒.
a battery pack on my chest.
你担心过一个完全处于试验阶段的设备,安装在你脑袋里吗？
Does it worry you that you have a totally experimental thing inside your brain？
不,不,因为这很值得.
No. No,because it's been worth it.
每当电脉冲释放一次,Diane的抑郁症就消失了.
From the very moment the electrodes were switched on,Diane's depression disappeared.
当然,你的生活就彻底改变了.
And of course your life has changed totally.
180度
180 degrees.
每天早上我醒来,我就想"今天我要处于什么状态？"
I wake up every day,and I think,"What's today going to bring？"
我对生活有着从来不曾有过的激情.
I have an excitement about living that I didn't ever have.
所以你是完美的仿生的女人？
So you're the perfect bionic woman？
是的,是的.
Yeah. Yes.
即使作为最后手段,将电子设备插入大脑中心深处的方式,
Even as a last resort,it seems utterly terrifying to think of
这种想法看上去似乎十分可怕,可是这就是Diane身上发生的.
thrusting an electronic device deep into the centre of the brain in the way that has happened with Diane.
但你不能挑剔它,因为它完全改变了她的生活.
But you can't knock it,because it's completely changed her life.
因为它改变生命和触及很多其他方面的能力,
Because of its power to transform lives and potential to touch many others,
仿生学肯定在我的榜单中.
bionics definitely has a place in my top ten.
这是不是过去50年来最重大的进步？
Is it the most significant advance of the last 50 years？
这由你在节目的末尾来决定.
That's up to you to decide at the end of the programme.
或者你再看看我的下一个选择 - 一个了不起的发明
Or maybe you'll go for my next choice - a remarkable invention
超越其他所有的,也许,能导致改变.
that more than any other,perhaps,has caused change.
它改变了我工作的方式.
It's changed the way I work.
它改变了我的发现新的艺术的方式.
It's changed the way I find out about new art.
跟踪我的孩子在做什么.
Keep track of what my kids are doing.
比较价格.查一查足球比分.
Compare prices. Look up football scores.
和朋友交谈.和女孩们聊天!
Talk to friends. Chat up girls!
为慈善事业筹集资金.看新闻
Raise money for charity. Watch the news.
它改变了研究的方式.
It's changed the way I do my research.
事实上,它通过无数种方式改变了我们的生活.
In fact,it's changed our lives in a thousand ways.
我,其中之一,也不能独善其身.
I,for one,couldn't do without it.
它就是互联网！
It is,of course,the World Wide Web!
想到我们大多数人第一次上线是在十年前,就让人觉得很吃惊.
It's astonishing to think that the majority of us went on-line for the very first time just ten years ago.
我第一次联上互联网是我在实验室
My first contact with the Internet was one day when I went into the lab
看我的中国博士研究生在她的屏幕上打字.
and saw my Chinese PhD student typing on her screen.
她在那儿打字,
And there she was,typing,
突然她的手离开了键盘.
and then suddenly she took her hands off the keyboard
在屏幕下方出现了一些字符.
and some other letters appeared just underneath.
她和香港的某个人在交流.
She was communicating with somebody in Hong Kong.
我想,"这绝不会过时"
I thought,"This will never take off!"
互联网要求世界上所有的电脑
The World Wide Web required all the computers in the world
使用同一种语言,以便能够相互交流.
to be able to talk to each other using one common language.
但是直到1990年之前这都不可能,一个名叫Tim Berners-Lee的英国科学家
But that was impossible until 1990,when a British scientist called Tim Berners-Lee
只出了一种连接所有人的方法.
figured out a way to link everybody up.
# Welcome to my world... #
他创造了一种代码让所有人可以交流.
He created a code allowing computers to share information.
一夜之间,我们就可以相互交流了.
And suddenly,we could speak to each other.
# Welcome to my world... #
一个新的信息交流时代开始了.
And a new age of communications began.
# Built with you in mind... #
由于网络从来没有申请专利,所以它是免费和开放给任何人使用.
Because the Web was never patented,it is free and open to anyone to use.
如今全球范围内有1.7亿人使用互联网.
Today,1.7 billion people use the web globally.
嗨大家好,今天我们要做一个好莱坞的嘴唇看.
Hi,everyone,today we're going to be doing a Hollywood lip look.
当你打算煮蛋却没有煮蛋器时,那就麻烦了.
When you're poaching eggs without an egg poacher,it can get messy.
如果你能像这样跳舞...
So if you can dance like this...
自从印刷术发明以来我们就没有见过这样的飞跃,
Not since the invention of the printing press
如此大量的信息给所有人免费使用.
have we seen such a leap forward in the amount of information freely available to everyone.
而以前从未有过这样一个平台让普通人发出他们的声音.
And never before has there been such a platform for ordinary people to make their voices heard.
这只是我的意见,你不同意,无所谓！
This is just my opinion,you disagree,feel free!
这是我们和朋友交流的方式.
It's how we communicate with friends.
我们中的一亿人使用社交网站
One billion of us using social networking sites
还有三百万人在虚拟世界碰面.
and 300 million meet people in a virtual world.
我们的孩子用它来进行互动,学习和玩耍.
Our children use it to interact,to learn and play.
它改变了新闻和信息.
It's transformed news and information.
在商业上,我们都变成商人,买卖东西只需点击一个按钮.
In business,we've all become traders,buying and selling at the click of a button.
对于接触暴力和色情的这些风险,令人担忧的问题我们必须面对,
For all the risk of exposure to violence and pornography,worrying issues we have to face,
互联网是过去50年来最重大的进步之一.
the Internet is one of the most significant advances of the past 50 years.
对我来说,网络是非常令人振奋,
And for me,the Web is exciting,
因为它允许我们以前所未有的方式参与到科学研究中.
because it allows all of us to participate in science like never before.
Chris Lintott博士的工作是对来自
Dr Chris Lintott has the task of classifying
机器人望远镜照片中上百万个星系进行分类.
over a million galaxies from photos taken by robotic telescopes.
这些数据量让他不堪重负,他聘请了数千名网上志愿者来帮助他.
He was so overwhelmed by the amount of data that he enlisted thousands of on-line volunteers to help him.
但真正令人兴奋的是,这些扶手椅上的科学家的新发现.
But the really exciting thing is that these armchair scientists made a new discovery.
几年前,一组志愿者注意到
A couple of years ago,a group of our volunteers noticed that
在一些图像的背景上有一些小的、圆的、绿色的点.
in the background of some of the images,there were these small,round,green objects.
他们称之为豌豆.志愿者们发现它们有数百个之多,"这都是些什么？"
They called them peas. They found a couple of hundred of them and said,"What are these？"
通过一些世界上最大的望远镜我们观测了它们.
We've looked at these with some of the world's largest telescopes.
它们是星系中的恒星经过剧烈爆发形成的.
They are galaxies undergoing a dramatic burst of star formation.
这是宇宙中制造恒星最有效的方式.
These are the most efficient makers of stars anywhere in the local universe.
它们被专业的天文学家忽略了.
They'd been missed by professional astronomers.
这要感谢上百万人,他们的扶手椅
It was only thanks to a quarter of a million people,their armchairs
和他们的网络连接,让我们发现了这些
and their Internet connections that they came to our attention.
星系动物园,只是一个邀请公众参与科学研究的项目服务器之一
Galaxy Zoo is just one of a host of projects inviting the public to get involved in science.
又有谁能知道互联网把这样的合作变为可能,
Who knows what progress we could make through
通过这种合作我们又能取得什么样的进展？
collaborations like these,made possible by the Internet？
这是人类信息交流的
This massive progress
巨大进步
in how humans exchange information
毫无疑问这是过去50年取得的一个决定性的进步
undoubtedly makes it one of the defining advances in the last 50 years.
互联网对我们生活产生的深远影响
Does the far-reaching impact of the World Wide Web on all our lives
是否使它成为最重要的进步？
make it the most significant advance？
或者革命性的人机互联意味着仿生学会赢得你的投票？
Or does the revolutionary joining of man with machine mean that biomechanics gets your vote？
如假包换的清洁能源会让激光成为你心目中的第一名？
Could it be the promise of clean energy for us all that makes the laser your number one？
你决定之前还有四个科学进步可以考虑.
Before you decide,there are four more advances to consider.
下一个有可能改变我们所相信的一切.
The next one has the potential to change everything we've ever believed in.
是什么让我们区别于其它动物呢？
What distinguishes us from all other creatures？
是人类的探索精神.
It's human inquisitiveness.
我们为什么在这里？ 我们会去哪里？
Why are we here？ Where are we going？
我们在宇宙的什么位置？
What's our place in the universe？
从天上俯瞰我们的这个世界,你会意识到我们有多么渺小.
Looking down on the world from above,you realise just how insignificant we are.
自从时间诞生,人们惊奇于
Since the dawn of time,people have marvelled
我们周围的辽阔并惊奇,"这些是如何开始的？"
at the vastness around us and wondered,"How did it all begin？"
在20世纪20年代,美国科学家Edwin Hubble
In the 1920s,American astronomer Edwin Hubble
发现了宇宙在膨胀,
showed that the universe was expanding,
基于这样一个简单的观测,
and from this simple observation,
如果你将时间倒流,通过计算
it was calculated that if you run the clock back...
所有的一切都诞生于140亿年前的一次大爆炸.
..everything must have exploded into existence nearly 14 billion years ago in a big bang.
对于我,一想到大爆炸这个充满想象力的想法,就感到激动.
For me,I suppose what I find so exciting about big bang is the ambition of the idea.
现在有一种想法,不仅仅关于我们的星球或我们的太阳系
Here is an idea that is not just about our planet or our solar system
而是统一我们对于整个宇宙的看法.
but unifies our whole notion of the universe.
它将告诉关于我们的起源,我们从哪儿来,还有可能回答我们会到哪儿去.
And it tells us about our beginnings,about where we came from and possibly to where we are going.
不过大爆炸理论还预言整个宇宙
But the big-bang theory also predicted that the entire universe,
所有的行星和星系,我们周围所看到的,来自于无.
all the planets and galaxies we see around us,exploded from nothing.
听起来很疯狂
Which sounds crazy.
当差不多100年前它首次提出时,这种想法还充满争议,
When it was first proposed almost 100 years ago,the idea was controversial,
但在过去50年中,科学已经开始收集到确凿的证据
but in the last 50 years,science has started to gather hard evidence
来证明大爆炸很可能不是一个疯狂的想法.
that the big bang might not be such a crazy idea after all.
1965年,两个在新泽西州卫星天线工作的
In 1965,two radio astronomers working on this satellite antenna
射电天文学家始终会接收到一个奇怪的信号.
in New Jersey started to pick up a strange signal.
这个无线电信号来自宇宙深空
This radiation was coming from somewhere
的任何方向.
in really deep cosmic space,
超过了我们任何已知的广播信号源
beyond any radio sources that any of us
甚至是幻想中的.
knew about or even dreamed existed.
这种辐射的大胆解释是它也许是
The daring explanation for the radiation was that it might be
大爆炸的最后遗迹回响在时间和空间里.
the last remnant of the big bang echoing through space and time.
也许
Perhaps.
2001年,WMAP探测器分析了这种辐射
In 2001,the WMAP spacecraft analysed this radiation
据此还绘制了一幅宇宙早期的图像
and even produced a map of the early universe
那看上去或多或少支持了大爆炸理论.
that seemed to more or less prove the big-bang theory.
但是遗憾的是,到目前为止,它并没有解释大爆炸发生的地方
But unfortunately,as yet,it doesn't explain why the big bang banged in the first place.
Lick天文台位于加州的高山上,天文学家正在试图计算宇宙膨胀的速度
High in the Californian hills at Lick Observatory,astronomers are trying to calculate
他们希望能够揭示一些光的问题.
how fast the universe is expanding,in the hope that they will be able shed some light on the problem.
并在这样做,他们有了一个惊人的发现.
And in doing so,they've made a surprising discovery.
人们预测引力会减慢
Everyone anticipated that gravity would slow down
宇宙膨胀的速度.
the expansion of the universe.
因此我们试图测量宇宙在多大程度上减缓
So we were trying to measure how much the universe has been slowing down
以便预测是会一直膨胀下去,还是越来越慢,或重新收缩.
in order to predict whether it will expand forever,though more and more slowly or re-collapse.
相反,我们发现宇宙在加速膨胀.一点儿也没有减慢下来.
Instead,we found that it's actually speeding up. Not slowing down at all.
一个加速中的宇宙
An accelerating universe.
它如何工作？为什么要做那个？
How does that work？ Why should it do that？
我们设想宇宙中充满了一种奇怪的东西,我们叫它暗能量,
Well,we think the universe is filled with some weird substance,we call it dark energy,
但实质上我们对它一无所知
but we know essentially nothing about it.
因此它的存在并在某种意义上,它是引力的反作用力
So it's there and in a sense,it's gravitationally repulsive,
导致空间膨胀随时间越来越快.
causing space to expand faster and faster with time.
这些都在表明宇宙正在膨胀,
It's all very well to say the universe is expanding,
但是有一个问题会让人们觉得迷惑,我们也膨胀吗？
but one of the questions that will puzzle a lot of people is,what are we expanding into？
那实际上让我们都感到迷惑.
That actually puzzles all of us.
我们可能会扩展到一个更大的超空间,一个有着更多维度的.
We may be expanding into a bigger hyperspace,one with more dimensions.
在这个更大的空间中也许有着各种各样的宇宙.
And there could be all sorts of universes expanding within this bigger space.
我们的宇宙只是多元宇宙中的一个.
And ours is just one of these universes in the multiverse.
我接受你正在做的是难以置信的有趣,但也没用,是不是？
I accept that you're doing is incredibly interesting,but it's useless,isn't it？
从某种意义上说,它是没用的,但是宇宙加速的性质是很重要的一部分
In a sense,it's useless,but the accelerating nature of the universe
因为它也许能帮助我们理解大爆炸.
is important in part because it may help us understand the big bang.
这是宇宙的诞生,
So it's the birth of the universe and so we should try to understand
我们可以试着理解它是如何发生的,宇宙从那时开始又是如何进化的.
how it is that it happened and how the universe has evolved since then.
但是,数据表明某些奇怪的,我相信,在这个阶段没有争议性.
But that the data are indicating something weird is,I believe,not controversial at this stage.
为什么大爆炸在我的科学进步名单中？
Why is big bang in my ten great ideas？
它具有象征意义
Well,it's symbolic.
它象征的一些我们人类独有的东西 -
It's symbolic of something that makes us uniquely human -
我们的探索精神.
our inquisitiveness.
而这促使我们,通过科学,不断向前.
And it's that which drives us,through science,forward.
我们已经大胆的踏入了外层空间,
We've had the audacity to tackle outer space,
但是我们从没有进入过内部空间.
but we've had the nerve to take on inner space too.
我的最后三项科学进步都是关于我们自身...
My final three advances are all about understanding us...
..源自一本2000年出版的书.
..starting with a remarkable book published in the year 2000.
115卷,就像这样
115 volumes like this
包含了一份完整的人类基因图,仅仅是一个人的.
contain the print-out of the human genome,from just one individual.
30亿个字母.
Three billion letters.
这是决定你是谁的配方.
It's the recipe for what makes you who you are.
这将彻底改变诊断、预防和大多数治疗方式,即便不是全部的人类的疾病
It will revolutionise the diagnosis,prevention and treatment of most,if not all,human diseases.
十年前,破译人类基因组的工作
Ten years ago,decoding the human genome
的重要性被誉为就像把人送上月球,
was hailed by many as as significant as putting a man on the moon,
是一个新千年希望的象征.
a symbol of the hope for the new millennium.
所有期望的原因是 - 有人甚至认为是“炒作” -
The reason for all the hope - and some would even say "hype" -
是因为基因治疗的巨大潜力.
was because of the enormous potential of gene therapy.
直到最近,医学也没有办法来恢复
Until recently,medicine could do nothing to restore
损坏或失灵的基因,但是今天,一些措施让我们看到了希望.
broken or malfunctioning genes,but today,there are some procedures which can offer hope.
十来岁的Abdullahi准备做手术,可能改变他的遗传的命运.
Ten-year-old Abdullahi is about to undergo an operation which might change his genetic destiny.
Abdullahi视力差,尤其是夜视能力
Abdullahi has poor vision,particularly poor night vision,
因为他缺乏的基因之一
because he lacks one of the genes
转换成神经脉冲光能量不可或缺的.
essential for converting light energy into a nerve impulse,
所以这次手术的目标是
so the idea of this operation
给他的视网膜提供一份该基因正确的、有功能的副本.
is to provide his retina with the correct,functioning copy of that gene.
为了做到这一点,我们把这段基因插入到去除毒性的病毒体内.
In order to do that,we package the genes themselves into a harmless virus.
但是要让病毒插入到正确的位置,
But to get the virus to the right place,
我们需要把病毒注入到视网膜的下方.
we need to inject the virus underneath the retina.
虽然他的外科医生不能确定,这样一个前沿治疗的效果如何,
Though his surgeon isn't certain how effective this cutting-edge treatment will be,
不进行干预,Abdullahi可能最终会完全失明.
without intervention,Abdullahi could eventually become totally blind.
但是这非凡的过程中希望实现的是
But what this remarkable procedure hopes to achieve
没有什么比提供一个新的、未损坏部分的DNA来代替
is nothing less than delivering a new,undamaged section of DNA to do the work
Abdullahi有缺陷基因来做这工作.
of Abdullahi's faulty gene.
好消息是,手术后,Abdullahi的视力开始提高.
The good news is that,since the operation,Abdullahi's vision has improved.
这只是基因治疗进程中的一小步,但是我们有理由相信,
It's a small step on the gene therapy journey,but its champions believe
它最终可能会给我们带来巨大的好处.
it could eventually have benefits for a great number of us.
成百上千个,不是吗？
It's got hundreds and thousands on it,hasn't it？
就像Millie和Ruby这样患有哮喘的孩子,在英国占到了约百分之十.
Like about ten per cent of children in the UK,Millie and Ruby suffer from asthma.
但是尽管这两个女孩的情况相似,
But while both girls have the condition,
Millie对药物的效果明显好于她的妹妹.
Millie responds a lot better to medication than her sister.
（RUBY咳嗽）
RUBY COUGHS
你有点咳嗽,是吗？你总是咳嗽吗？
You've got a bit of a cough,haven't you？ Do you always have a cough？
对于Ruby,攻击导致无休止的进医院,并可能是致命的
'For Ruby,attacks result in endless dashes to hospital and could be fatal.'
（RUBY咳嗽）
RUBY COUGHS
面对你孩子的情况你无能为力.
There is nothing you can do to help your child.
你想,"Ruby在某些时候,她会停止呼吸？"
You think,"At some point,is she going to stop breathing？"
她们咳嗽这么多,她们正在生病,
They are coughing so much that they are being sick,
她们的呼吸变得糟糕,你就得送她们去医院.
their breathing becomes worse and then you are going to hospital,
这是你能想象到的最糟糕的感觉.
it is the worst feeling you can imagine.
但是Ruby是相当有活力性格,是不是？
But Ruby's quite a resilient character,isn't she？
当然
Absolutely.
她很让人吃惊. 甚至当她最糟糕的时候,她也会给你一个微笑.
She's amazing. Even when she's at her worst,she'll give you a smile.
Millie 和 Ruby 参与了一个研究项目
Millie and Ruby are taking part in a research project
该项目研究为什么某些病人比其他病人更容易痊愈.
which is trying to discover why some patients are easier to treat than others.
在英国
Over 100,000 children
超过10万儿童哮喘患者
in the United Kingdom with asthma
携带者一个特定的变异基因
carry a particular gene change
让她们似乎更加敏感
which seems to make them much less responsive
对常见的哮喘药吸入器,我们使用的蓝色吸入器.
towards the commonest asthma-reliever inhaler,the blue inhaler that we use.
Swabs采样这对女孩的DNA,她们的基因,进行检测.
Swabs are taken so that the girls' DNA,their genes,can be examined.
希望药物能和她们的基因相匹配,
The hope is that medicines can be matched to genes,
目前的试错方法来治疗
and that the current trial-and-error approach
像Ruby这样的人将成为历史.
to treating people like Ruby will be a thing of the past.
这个梦想是,最终,我们都会与药物治疗
The dream is that,eventually,we'll all be treated with medicines
与我们自己拥有的DNA完美的匹配.
that are a perfect match for our own unique DNA.
这项技术得以发展是受益于人类基因组项目
The technology that's developed since the human genome project means
排列个人基因图将变得越来越容易和经济.
that decoding an individual's genome is becoming easier and affordable.
遗传学知识,是一个崭新的领域,理解我们的基因如何工作
Genetic knowledge is a new frontier and our understanding of how genes work
是自古代希腊时代最重要的医学进步之一.
is one of the most significant medical advances since the time of Ancient Greece.
这种方法的采用将彻底改变疾病治疗中的用药.
The methods it employs have applications that will revolutionise the treatment of disease.
Imperial学院的科学家在实验室里
Scientists working in this lab at Imperial College
正试图找到一个终结人类疾病的治疗.
are trying to find a cure for a devastating human disease.
但是他们并不是开发新药,他们正试图了解如何长出新的组织.
But they're not developing medicines,they are trying to understand how to grow new tissues.
我的同事 Michael Schneider是这一研究的国际领先者,
My colleague Michael Schneider is a world leader in this research,
他和他的团队已经取得了显著的进步.
and he and his team have made a remarkable advance.
他们从零开始培养出了跳动的心脏细胞.
They've created beating-heart cells from scratch.
当你俯下身从显微镜中第一眼
When you first looked down the microscope
看到一个跳动的心脏细胞.
and saw a heart cell beating,
你的反应是什么？
what was your reaction？
当你看到这样的一群
When you see a cluster like this,
在培养皿中有力的跳动,
beating vigorously in the dish,it obviously stimulates your thinking
这显然会刺激你去思考,如何应用这些信息,到复杂的心肌修复中的临床应用.
about how to apply that information to the complicated task of cardiac muscle repair in a clinical setting.
十天前,这些
Ten days ago,those kinds of cells
未分化的胚胎干细胞
were undifferentiated embryonic stem cells
能不受限制的分化成身体的任何细胞.
that can become any cell in the body without restriction.
当卵子受精时就产生了第一个干细胞.
Stem cells are among the first cells produced when an egg is fertilised.
虽然开始时它们长的一模一样
Though they start off looking the same,
很快它们就变成截然不同的东西 -
they soon turn into very different things -
骨骼、肌肉、头发、牙齿,神经,
bone,muscle,hair,teeth,nerves,
所有不同类型的细胞构成了一个人.
all the different cell types that make up a human being.
通过了解这些转化如何运作的,
By understanding how these transformations work,
像Michael这样的科学家,试图找到如何修补损伤或病变器官的方法.
scientists like Michael are trying to find out how to repair damaged or diseased organs.
因此这项工作在干细胞领域中有多么重要？
So how important is this work in the field of stem cell biology？
观看这个节目的人中40%将死于心血管疾病.
40% of the people watching this programme will die of cardiovascular disease.
值得注意的是,心脏病实际上是细胞死亡,而没有新细胞来替换,
Taking that together with the fact that heart disease boils down to cell death without cell replacement,
这就可以通过干细胞修复心脏
that makes cardiac repair by stem cells
这是干细胞研究领域中
one of the most important and promising areas
最重要最有前途的领域.
for stem cell research.
到目前为止,已经因为对干细胞研究
So far,there have been few treatments developed
而发展出一些治疗方法,但一些研究人员甚至希望他们最终将能够
because of work on stem cells,but some researchers even hope that eventually they'll be able
用培植器官来替换,或至少帮助身体自我修复.
to grow replacement organs,or at least help the body repair itself.
极少数人反对人类胚胎研究,因为它破坏人类胚胎.
A tiny minority are opposed to human embryo research because it damages human embryos.
他们有道理,但实际上我认为这是道义,
They have a point,but to my mind it's actually an ethical imperative
试图拯救生命,这是一个方法.
to try to save lives and this is one way of doing it.
'我最后的科学进步是非常接近我的心.
'My final scientific advance is very close to my heart.
'这是一些我职业生涯中最投入的
'It's something to which I've devoted most of my career.
'每一个这些儿童的生命开始于一个试管
'Every single one of these children's lives began in a test tube
'或培养皿. 他们是试管婴儿.他们不是在子宫里,而是在实验室里成为受精卵'
'or a dish. They are IVF children. They come from eggs fertilised not in the womb but in the laboratory.'
这真可怕！
That was really frightening!
'如果不是因为生命科学研究的最早阶段,他们不会在这里.'
'None of them would be here if it wasn't for scientific research into the earliest stages of life.'
嗯,这是粉红色的.这不是真正的红色.
Well,it is sort of pink. It's not really red.
你想要粉色,现在？ 不？ 你很特别！
Would you allow pink,then？ No？ You're very particular!
'虽然我曾参与了这项研究,
'And although I was involved in that research,
'我必须承认,在当时,我没有意识到它的重要性.'
'I have to confess that,at the time,I didn't appreciate its significance.'
我并没有想到它会真的变得如此重要.
I didn't think it was really going to be very important.
我没有想到试管婴儿是一项科技
I didn't think that IVF was a technology
这真的可以用来治疗不育症.
that would really make any difference to infertility treatment.
看看我曾犯了多大的错误……
Look how wrong I was...
这些孩子.他们是世界上上百万个试管婴儿中的一些.
all these babies. There are about a million IVF babies around the world.
在二十世纪八十年代,我和我的同事开发了一个实验
In the 1980s,my colleagues and I developed an experimental IVF technique
来筛选试管婴儿技术在胚胎发育的遗传疾病.
to screen for genetic diseases in the developing embryo.
Christine Munday的第一个孩子Justin,是一个重度残疾人,
Christine Munday's first son Justin was severely handicapped,
发现她携带有遗传病
and it was discovered that she carries a genetic condition
这意味着她的任何一个儿子非常有可能
which means it is very likely that any of her male children
继承同样的问题.
would inherit the same problems.
为取得这一突破,我们已经努力了9年
We've been trying for nine years
使我们今后可以有机会.
for this breakthrough to come so that we could have another chance.
1990年,我们筛选了她受精胚胎,以确保她有一个女孩.
In 1990,we screened her fertilised embryos to ensure that she had a girl.
Rebecca现在19岁了.
Rebecca is now 19.
你妈妈是非常勇敢.我不知道你能否意识到这一点,
Your mum was wonderfully brave. I don't know if you realise that,
因为我们当时所作的是
because what we were doing was
纯粹的实验,我们不知道这样做是否有用
a very,very experimental procedure and we had no idea if it was going to
你还记得,我们不能保证你会有一个不受影响的孩子.
work or not. As you remember,we couldn't guarantee that you wouldn't have a child who wasn't affected.
不.对于我,那不是勇敢,你知道,孩子可能会以某种方式出现缺陷,
No. To us,it wasn't brave,you know,the baby could have been damaged
但我从来没有担心过那边一点.
in some way but I never,ever worried about that side of it at all.
我有充分的信心,相信你会成功的.
I had my whole confidence that you would actually get it right.
是啊,有趣,不是吗？我当时可没什么信心.
Yeah,funny,isn't it？ I don't think that I had that confidence.
作为一个体外受精的孩子是否让你感觉有什么不同？
Does having been born as a result of in vitro fertilisation make you feel any different？
我很感动.
I'm quite humbled.
我们的家庭,这是很重要的突破.
For our family,it's been quite crucial for this breakthrough.
你知道？当然,当然.
You know？ Of course,of course.
如果不那样做,今天我就不会有Rebecca.她不总是这么说.
I wouldn't have Rebecca today if it wasn't for that. She doesn't always say that.
对于我,见到你的时候,真的很感人.
For me,it's genuinely a very moving occasion actually to meet you.
对我来说非常特别.
Very special for me.
'20年前,有相当多的人反对这项工作'
'20 years ago,there was considerable opposition from people hoping to stop such work.'
那是什么？
What's that？
那是你吗？
Was that you？
'但是在英国,立法非常迅速.
'But in the UK,legislation was hugely positive.
'它使我们带来希望,不仅仅是像Christine,而是成千上万
'And it has enabled us give hope,not just to people like Christine,but also to hundreds of thousands
'由于某种原因没有孩子的家庭.'
'of families who otherwise couldn't have had children.'
ALL: Cheese!
好了,这就是我的科学进步名单.现在该你说了.
Well,that concludes my list. Now it's time for you to have your say.
刚才观看过的十大科学进步中你认为那一项是最重要的？
Which of the ten scientific advances we've looked at do you think is the most important？
是创造了上百万生命的试管婴儿,或是给予厚望的干细胞研究？
Is it the millions of lives created by IVF,or the huge promise of stem cell research？
拯救生命的MRI是你的最爱？
Is your favourite the life-saving MRI machine？
或是强大的微芯片？
Or the mighty microchip？
你认为避孕药为我们做的,比高能激光多得多？
Do you think the contraceptive pill has done more for us than the giant laser ever will？
或者更能鼓舞你的是能够重建我们自己的仿生学？
Or is it our ability to rebuild ourselves with bionics that inspires you the most？
你能说全球互联网的力量,能击败读懂拥有巨大潜力的我们的基因图？
Can you say the global power of the Internet beats the huge potential of understanding more about our genes？
抑或是令人难以置信的大爆炸理论胜过它们？
Or does the mind-boggling big-bang theory trump them all？
到我们的网站上
Go to our website to vote for the scientific advance
投出你心目中的最重大科学进步. 访问...
you think has been the most significant. Visit...
在网站上有十大科学进步的提示.
There's a reminder of the top ten advancements on the website.
在你上网投票前.我觉得我得先把我的卡放在桌子上.
Before you vote on-line,I feel I should put my cards on the table.
我不愿说这十大科学进步哪一个是我的最佳
I'm reluctant to say which of these ten advances is my greatest,
只是可能,我可能会选择大爆炸的研究.
but just possibly,I might plump for the research on big bang.
似乎没用,但它带来的知识
It might seem useless,yet the knowledge it brings
几乎、肯定会对人类产生无法预料的影响.
will almost certainly have unforeseen consequences for humanity.
也许,了解宇宙要好一点
Just possibly,understanding the universe a little better
会帮助我们这个物种继续蓬勃发展.
will help our species to continue to flourish.
字幕：Red Bee Media Ltd
Subtitles by Red Bee Media Ltd
E-mail subtitling@bbc.co.uk